Guide to the Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection, 1947-1982 and undated RL.10157
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Films, 1947-1976; 1
  - TreeTops, Tanzania, Kenya, Safari Club / Safari, Ngorongoro Crater, Durban, Zulu Land, 1971 October, 27; 29.41 minutes
    • cartoon drawings of Dorothy and Morris with a huge lion between them • entrance to Mount Kenya Safari & Game Ranch • Morris stands next to sign: "Mount Kenya Safari Club" • Morris in field • landscapes • Dorothy in garden • views of sports club and garden area • unidentified couple goofs around, bumps into Dorothy • sign: "Danger / Wild Animals / Stay in Your vehicle / No Pedestrians / Speed Limit 15 Miles Per Hour" • animals, some in cages others on safari: warthogs, antelopes, giraffes, leopards, monkeys, gorillas, dik-diks, zebras • antelope? approaches car, sticks head in the window • exterior of Outspan Hotel • Dorothy sits at table • people gather in outdoor café • Dorothy and group on tour, at least one man with a rifle • landscapes, some with animals • Dorothy looks out over landscape from bridge • landscapes, some with animals • Dorothy and group on lookout bridge • close-ups on birds • Dorothy and group eat snacks from table • landscapes, some with animals • Dorothy with group of locals selling beaded necklaces • close-ups on locals • rural village • small child walks toward camera, herding animals? • landscapes, some with animals (including rhinos) • sand storm • group of identical tent-like structures • Dorothy walks out of tent #15 • Dorothy with group of locals behind her • sign: "KENYA / This Sign is on the Equator" • Dorothy near sign, small market on other side of dirt road • Morris points to equator sign • sign: "Welcome to Tanzania" • landscapes, many with villagers • city street • directional signs • exterior of New Arusha Hotel • informal roadside market • clock tower • sign: "Meru Tavern Bar" • street scenes, including women carrying bundles on their heads • Dorothy walks toward camera, lawn chairs and pool nearby, hills and water in background • landscapes • exterior of Lake Manyara Hotel • zebra-painted buses • landscapes • back of white car with license plate KLL 65 • entry gate with animal skull on fence • sign: "Lake Manyara National Park" • pathway and sign: "Take No Liberties with Dangerous Animals" • white car and zebra painted buses in lot • Dorothy walks toward building • landscapes with animals, including rhino with baby, hyena, flock of birds, lion, jackals, gazelles, wildebeest?, zebras, and others • sign: "Headquarters / Ngorongoro Conservation Unit" • a few locals stand along road, one by car -- perhaps at the Conservation Unit? • Lake Manyara? and environs, including wildlife such as zebras, birds, antelope, gazelles, lioness, buffalo, elephants, and others • young people approach camera, selling necklaces • group of tourists with cameras • children (some naked) run along road, approach camera, hold out hands • group of naked children dance • bare-breasted woman selling necklaces • huts on hillside • Dorothy exits bus • flowers and foliage • group enters Ben's Den • cheetah or leopard? in the shade • village and villagers • bare-breasted women • Dorothy poses with villagers • villagers gather, perform
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 29.41 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0002)
  - France, Hungary, 1975, 28; 33.06 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0003 France, Hungary, 1975, 1975 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 33.06 minutes
    • street scenes in France • exterior of Hotel Inter-Continental • man directs traffic, street scenes • Dorothy across the street, cars whiz past • exterior of Hotel Meurice, Paris • golden statue of person on horse • group plays bocce ball in park • sidewalk scenes, gardens • fountain, possibly Tuileries Garden? • Arc du Carrousel • statues in park • exterior of Louvre, close-up on lion statues flanking door • scenes of the Seine River • street scenes • Dorothy on sidewalk, next to yellow vehicle • street scenes • priest? standing by lamppost • dogs playing in park, possibly Jardin du Luxembourg? • Dorothy sunbathing on deck near pool • view of ocean, harbor, coastline from pool deck • pool side bar • Dorothy reads paper in lounge chair on deck • skyline, pans to boats in harbor • views of French? coastline • Dorothy walks to unidentified building • signs: "Golfe-Juan / Syndicat d'Initiative" and "Cannes P.T.T." • street scenes • Dorothy exist building, walks toward camera • street scenes • boats in harbor • palm trees and pedestrians along promenade • boats in harbor • close-up on boat: "Komati Southampton" • Dorothy near gate on dock • title: "Boats boats boats!" • close-up on water • views of coastline, water, ocean liner, sailboat • beachgoers wade into water, sunbathe on rocks • views of coastline, water, harbor • abstract sculpture and mosaic on building • Dorothy walks out of unidentified building, possibly an art museum? • artwork in museum, some is underexposed • sidewalk scene, Dorothy at café • beach scenes, including nearby promenade • exterior of Palais des Festivals et des Congres, Cannes • couple eats at beachside café • Dorothy exits InterContinental Carlton Cannes • sign: "Carlton Beach" • beach scenes • close-up on exterior of unidentified building • beach scenes, including a number of topless sunbathers • kids ride bicycles in city square • pigeons gather around woman with cane seated on bench • buildings along river? and suspension bridges in Hungary? • exteriors of building, possibly Buda Castle, under construction • close-up on lion statue • exteriors of building under construction • statue littered with rubble • pieces of statue on ground • sign: "Magyar Munkasmozgalmi Muzeum" • exteriors of building • street and sidewalk scenes • statue in city square • Dorothy talks to a woman in courtyard, kids learn over banister • close-up: street number "66" • exterior of Inter-Continental • scenes of Heroes' Square, including tour group and uniformed men • hazy views of Budapest skyline, Danube River • street scenes, including Dorothy walking with tour group • sign: "(visual) no dogs" • Fisherman's Bastion • hazy views of Budapest skyline, Danube River • Dorothy walks toward unidentified building with woman • Danube River and buildings on opposite bank • traffic as seen from tour bus? • directional sign: "Esztergom, Visegrad" • cemetery? • sign: "Autobusz / Panorama / Buszmegallo a Fellegvarhoz / Bushaltestelle Zur Citadelle" • mountainside, views of rural Danube River • close-up on ruins on mountaintop • Dorothy talks to woman on sidewalk • women sit on bench • ruins on mountaintop • Dorothy still talking to woman on sidewalk • boat pulls away from dock • structure, possibly ruins, on hillside • aerial views of countryside • Dorothy and friends? pose for camera • Dorothy and friends? walk along rural road • directional sign, difficult to read • directional sign: "Etterem Restaurant" • ruins on hilltop • sign: "Pilisi Parkerdo, and others" • aerial view of Danube River • Dorothy and friends? wander around ruins • views of countryside • sign in Hungarian • small group gathers at roadside • woman sells wares at small table • tour bus and tour group in parking lot • directional sign: "WC" • fortress on hilltop • scenes of Danube River • sign in Hungarian • scenes of Danube River, fortress on hilltop • directional sign: "Budapest, Esztergom" • Dorothy sits on bench, smoking • signs in Hungarian • small boats on Danube River • passengers, including Dorothy, on ferry • views of countryside from river • man with dachshund on shore • Dorothy on street in small Hungarian town • suburban, arguably rural, street scenes • sign: "Beszallas Budapest Fele" • sign: "MHRT Nagymaros" • buildings alone Danube in Budapest • Dorothy poses for camera • Budapest street scenes
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 33.06 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0003)
  - Munich - Germany, 1975, 29; 16.03 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0004 Munich - Germany, 1975 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 16.03 minutes
    • exterior of Hotel Vier Jahreszeiten • street scenes • sign: "Nationaltheater" • National Theater in Munich, Germany • street scenes, including U-bahn entrance • traditional Bavarian architecture • flower market • street scenes of downtown Munich • window of butcher shop • street scenes, including outdoor market • buildings with Lowenbrau logo • more scenes from the outdoor market • sign: "Kartoffel Verkauf (Potato Sale)" • sign: "Marienplatz / Tal" • Munich street scenes • street sign: "Ludwigstrasse" • traffic • sign: "Neue pinakothek / Staatsgalerie moderner kunst" • statue outside of neue pinakothek • artwork in neue pinakothek, most underexposed • exterior of unidentified building, including close-ups on damage • sidewalk scenes, including group gathered to watch…? • directional sign: "Olympia-Radstadion, Leichtathletikhalle, Olympiastadion" • Munich's Olympic facilities • sidewalk scenes in Munich shopping district • glockenspiel at Marienplatz • sidewalk scenes, including close-up on Hirmer • Dorothy window-shopping at jewelry store • sign: "Schmuck Uhren Huber Trauringe" • sidewalk scenes • more of Munich's Olympic facilities, including Olympichalle and Olympicstadion • exterior of Hofbrauhaus
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 16.03 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0004)
  - Romania / Bucharest, Bulgaria / Sofia, Yugoslavia / Zagreb, 1975, 30; 23.21 minutes
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 23.21 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0005)
  - London, 1976 July, 31; 16.24 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0006 London, July 1976 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 16.24 minutes
    • Dorothy sitting in stadium with others • head leaders • British flag on rooftop, highway in background • aerial view of city and surroundings • unidentified building • street scenes, including double decker red buses • Dorothy walks through gate • street scenes • sign: "Knightsbridge Spaghetti House" • sidewalk and street scenes • exteriors of Hyde Park Hotel • The Scotch House / Burberry's on London corner • street scene, with Harrod's in distance • Dorothy walks along sidewalk, walks into purse shop • visit to unidentified site, outside of London? • sunbathers on lawn • signs for Cafeteria, Ladies • Big Ben, Palace of Westminster from across the Thames • Gresham Street, London • Guildhall • sign: "Site of Blackwell Hall, 1356-1820" • exteriors of buildings • interiors of church? including stained glass windows • Dorothy on street outside of The George Inn • performance at outdoor theater • sign: "The Dickens House Library & Museum" • residential street, sign on building: "Stable Yard" • sign on building: "Stable Yard" • Queen's Guardsman in distance • Little St. James's Street, London • Selwyn House • views of buildings, rose garden • street scenes • sign: "Mariscos" • Dorothy and couple at café table • Greenwich Park overlooking London, views of Queen's House? • statue at park • sign: "Prime Meridian of the World" • Royal Observatory • exteriors of National Maritime Museum • River Thames? • exteriors of unidentified building, possibly Royal Naval College? • friend pouts and walks toward camera • Cutty Sark and environs • Gipsy Moth IV • friend hams it up for the camera • Royal Naval College • restaurant: The Bull at Bisham • grounds of the Compleat Angler Hotel • Dorothy and couple at café • River Thames in Marlow • George Dragon Hotel, High Wycombe • street scenes, including British police • Dorothy and couple walks through gardens • grounds and exterior of unidentified residence • sign: "Thames Conservancy NOTICE" • boats on dock • family walks along shaded path • Dorothy and couple along bank of River Thames • Spread Eagle Hotel and environs • sidewalk and street scenes in small town • building: "The Wheatsheaf? Fine Horsham Ales" • clock tower / rotunda • bulletin board for Chichester Cathedral • people at park, pans to street scenes • Chichester Cathedral, West Sussex?; under renovation • city square • Horse Guards Avenue, City of Westminster • posted schedule for changing of the Queen's Life Guard • Queen's Guard • street scenes, including unidentified building • more shots of Queen's Guard; Dorothy approaches guard on horseback • street scenes in London?
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 16.24 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0006)
  - Rhine River Cruise / Majorca, 1976 July, 32; 28.34 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0007 Rhine River Cruise, Majorca, July 1976 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 28.34 minutes
    • harbor and other boats (one with German flag), shot from boat • church on riverbank • street scenes, blurry signs… one is for Hauptbahnhof • Dorothy and young woman on sidewalk • exterior of hotel, name is blurry • Dorothy and young woman walk toward hotel • young kids play in fountain • sidewalk scenes • close-ups of cathedral in Cologne, Germany • Dorothy and woman near café • Dorothy boards bus • people on deck of river boat • boats (one is labeled 150 Jahre Koln-Dusseldorfer), riverbank from boat • Dorothy and young woman walk down hallway • boats, bridges, riverbank shot from boat • interior of boat, Dorothy and young couple sit at café • passengers on deck of boat • flags lowered • Dorothy and others look out over boat deck • more scenes from the boat trip • young girl jumps down steps, art propped up along sidewalk • sidewalk and street scenes • building: "Correos Y Telegrafos" (Posts and telegraphs) • building: "Caja Portal de Amorros" • Dorothy window-shops • sidewalk and street scenes • sign for Air France • billboard: "Dinero de verano / Banco de Bilbao" • Dorothy walks toward camera • scenes of narrow street • poster: "Maria del mar Bonet" • man points to words written on wall, Dorothy and young woman nearby • woman seated on balcony • aerial view of street scenes • sign: "La Loza Mallorquina Juan Canals No. 7" • sidewalk scenes, shops • street scenes • boats in small inlet, nearby hotel • close-ups on boats in inlet • blurry sign • hotel pool • close-ups on boats in inlet • docked boats, including large boat: Stena Germanica • harbor, dock, nearby roads • passengers on Stena Germanica • another large boat: Santa Cruz de Tenerife • skyline, including fortress on hilltop • visit to fortress • close-ups on cathedral • Dorothy and young woman walk along sidewalk • sidewalk and street scenes, including art shop • Dorothy and others explore gardens? • beach scenes, back to the small inlet with boats • Dorothy on balcony overlooking inlet • beach scenes, sunbathers and boats in inlet • hotel pool and surrounding landscapes • buildings and environs, some shot from car • group rides by on horses • airplane building? • sign: "Bar Restaurante Pour Redo" • pile of unknown construction elements • view of ocean and surrounding landscape, including a shots of Dorothy with an unidentified man • woman walks to hotel pool • sidewalk and street scenes, including a number of signs in German, also Spanish • field of trees • small town streets captured from car • building: "Casa Consistorial" • unidentified church and environs • ocean and coast • buildings under construction • gardens and natural landscapes • hotel pool and environs, including hillside • sunbathers and swimmers at the hotel pool, including Dorothy • young girls walk down street in village • wandering around streets of small village, shots of natural environs • nuns in small village • more wandering and shots of natural environs
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 28.34 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0007)
- Travel Slides Series, 1959-1982 and undated; 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  In addition to creating film travelogs, the Margolins took many color photographs in the same countries, and had them formatted into color slides which they would then load into carousel trays and project at special gatherings. The vivid color images feature many kinds of buildings, inhabitants, street scenes, tourist sites, and natural landscapes. Occasionally Dorothy and Morris Margolin, family, and friends make an appearance.
  The earliest images were taken in France in 1959, and the latest dates are of a 1982 trip to Italy. Of particular interest are over 200 hundred slides from Russia taken in the 1960s, and many images of Israel from the 1960s and 1971, as well as slides from South Africa during the apartheid era. There are also images from Florence in 1968, showing the consequences of the devastating flood of 1966. Other locations cover most of Europe and England, parts of Southeast Asia, Africa, and a few locations in the U.S. and Canada.
  The over 4000 slides, arranged in chronological order and then alphabetically by country, were originally in carousel trays; their original projection sequencing has been preserved to the extent possible.
  - French Riviera / Paris, France / Majorca and Barcelona, Spain, 1959, 69 items (Box 5)
  - Italy, 1959 and 1967, 60 items (Box 5)
    Includes Florence, Verona, Rome, Villa D'Este, and Como.
  - France, 1964, 50 items (Box 5)
    Images are from Paris.
  - Greece, 1964, 74 items (Box 5)
  - Israel, 1964 (tray 1), 80 items (Box 5)
    A note on the carousel box for Tray 1 of 2 says "With Eleanor and Kal [?]."
  - Israel, 1964 (tray 2), 78 items (Box 9)
  - Italy, 1964, 70 items (Box 5)
    Includes Colombo, Naples, and Taormina.
  - Yugoslavia and Finland, 1964, 40 items (Box 9)
  - USSR/Family, 1964-1967, 80 items (Box 5)
  - USSR, 1964 and 1967, 73 items (Box 5)
    Images are from Moscow. A handwritten note on the carousel box says "Sound on tape."
  - USSR, 1964-1967, 80 items (Box 5)
    Includes Moscow and Leningrad. A note on the carousel box says "Excellent," and "Sound on tape."
  - Hong Kong / Kaloon (Kowloon), 1965, 59 items (Box 9)
  - Hong Kong, 1965?, 8 items (Box 5)
  - Italy and Portugal, 1965, 42 items (Box 5)
  - Japan, 1965, 76 items (Box 5)
    Includes Fuji-Hakone National Park and Osaka.
  - Japan, 1965, 72 items (Box 5)
    Includes Tokyo and Hiroshima.
  - Japan, 1965, 51 items (Box 9)
  - Japan - Kyoto, Dogo Spa, 1965, 69 items (Box 5)
  - Pakistan - Karachi, Hawaii, and San Francisco, 1965, 66 items (Box 5)
  - Thailand, 1965, 69 items (Box 5)
  - Thailand - Bangkok, 1965, 80 items (Box 5)
  - Turkey, 1965, 60 items (Box 9)
  - USSR, Sochi, 1967, 48 items (Box 9)
  - France, 1967, 73 items (Box 5)
    Scenes from Paris and the Riviera.
  - France - Deauville; Prague, Czechoslovakia, 1967, 79 items (Box 6)
  - USSR, 1967, 80 items (Box 6)
    Includes Yalta and Kiev.
  - Italy - Venice, 1967, 46 items (Box 6)
  - Ireland, 1968, 82 items (Box 6)
  - England - London, 1968, 85 items (Box 9)
  - Italy, 1968, 61 items (Box 6)
    Includes Milan and Rome.
  - Italy after the floods, 1968, 52 items (Box 6)
    Includes Verona and Florence.
  - Italy, 1968 and 1972, 62 items (Box 6)
    Includes Sestri Levante, Montecatini, Portofino, and Lucca.
  - Italy - Rome, 1968, 76 items (Box 6)
  - France, 1969 November, 77 items (Box 6)
    Includes Paris and the Riviera.
  - Gibraltar, Morocco, 1969, 126 items (Box 6)
  - Spain, 1969 November, 60 items (Box 6)
  - Spain, 1969, 92 items (Box 6)
    Includes Granada, Seville, Madrid.
  - Italy - Capri, 1971 September, 105 items (Box 6)
    Includes a few slides from Holland, 1971 Nov.
  - Africa, 1971 October, 131 items (Box 7)
    Includes Nairobi, Johannesburg, Capetown, and Durban.
  - Addis Ababa, Africa, 1971 October, 76 items (Box 7)
  - African safari, 1971 October, 118 items (Box 7)
    Includes Kenya, Tanzania, Zululand, and South Africa.
  - Israel, 1971 October, 142 items; 2 folders (Box 7)
    Includes Jerusalem, Jericho, and Tel Aviv.
  - France, 1972, 91 items (Box 7)
  - Italy, 1972, 140 items; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Munich, Germany; Zagreb, Yugoslavia, 1972 September or October, 118 items (Box 7)
  - Switzerland, 1972, 62 items (Box 7)
    Includes Basel, Bern, and Geneva.
  - Switzerland, 1972 October, 136 items (Box 7)
    Includes Zermatt and Zurich.
  - Bucharest, Romania, Sofia, Bulgaria, and Budapest, Hungary, 1975 September-October, 171 items; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - France, 1975 September, 138 items; 2 folders (Box 8)
    Includes Paris and Cannes.
  - Germany - Rhine River Cruise, 1976 July, 67 items (Box 8)
  - England - London, 1976, 26 items (Box 8)
  - Majorca, and Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1976 July, 125 items; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - England, 1980 July, 129 items; 2 folders (Box 8)
    Includes Bournemouth, Bath, and Stratford-upon-Avon.
  - England, 1980 (July?), 65 items (Box 9)
  - Canadian Rockies, 1981 July, 186 items (Box 8)
  - Italy, 1982, 127 items; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Puerto Rico, 1950s?, 44 items (Box 9)